Thomy Phan

Curriculum Vitae

Contact Information

Email

thomy.phan@usc.edu Website thomyphan.github.io

Research Interests

I am interested in various topics related to artificial intelligence, such as multi-agent systems, machine learning, pattern recognition, bio-inspired algorithms, automated planning, optimization, as well as validation and verification of self-learning systems. My current research focuses on multi-agent learning for optimization of large-scale distributed and intelligent systems such as warehouse automation, fleet management, and drone delivery.

Education

2018 - 2023

Ph.D. in Computer Science, LMU Munich, Germany

- Thesis: "Emergence and Resilience in Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning"
 - Thesis committee: Claudia Linnhoff-Popien, Sven Koenig, Long Tran-Thanh
 - Based on work published at AAMAS, AAAI, IJCAI, NeurIPS, and ICML

2015 - 2017

M.Sc. in Computer Science, LMU Munich, Germany

- Focus on artificial intelligence, data science, and autonomous systems
- Master thesis: "EVADE: Emergent Value Function Approximation for Distributed Environments"
 - Supervision: Claudia Linnhoff-Popien, Lenz Belzner
 - Results published at AAMAS 2018 as a full conference paper

2011 - 2015

B.Sc. in Computer Science, *Munich University of Applied Sciences*, Germany

- Collaborative study program (duales Studium) with the City of Munich
- Focus on software development and image processing
- Bachelor thesis: "Quantification and Feature Extraction of 3D Single-Molecule Switching Microscopy Data"
 - Supervision: Alfred Nischwitz, Joerg Bewersdorf
 - Practical work done at Bewersdorf Lab, Yale School of Medicine
 - Results published in Cell 2016 as a journal paper (cover story)

Professional Experience

2023 - Present

Postdoctoral Scholar, University of Southern California, Los Angeles, CA, USA

- Advisor: Sven Koenig
- Focus on multi-agent learning for optimization.

2017 - 2023

Research Assistant, LMU Munich, Germany

- Advisor: Claudia Linnhoff-Popien
- Focus on emergence and resilience in multi-agent systems.

Thomy Phan 1/7 2015 – 2018 **Software Developer**, *it@M*, *City of Munich*, Germany Development, maintainance, and integration of business applications (part-time).

Internships

- 2015 Visiting Scholar in Research (3 Months), Yale University, New Haven, CT, USA
 - Advisor: Joerg Bewersdorf
 - Focus on data analysis and feature extraction of cellular structures in super-resolution microscopy data. Co-authored publication in Cell 2016 (cover story).
- 2012 2014 Working Student (Collaborative Study Program), City of Munich, Germany Regular internships focusing on IT architecture, project management, and software development during the semester holidays.

Honors and Awards

- 2022 **Premier Paper of AAMAS 2022**, Journal of the International Foundation for Autonomous Agents and Multi-Agent Systems (JAAMAS)

 Fast-track invitation to submit an extended version of our AAMAS 2022 paper "Emergent Cooperation from Mutual Acknowledgment Exchange" (main author).
- 2022 **Highlight Paper at the Workshop on Ad Hoc Teamwork**, *International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI)*, Vienna, Austria Recognition of our AAMAS 2022 paper "Emergent Cooperation from Mutual Acknowledgment Exchange" (main author).
- 2022 **Top 10% Reviewer**, International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), Baltimore, MD, USA
- 2021 **ICAART 2021 Springer Selection**, Lecture Notes in Artificial Intelligence Fast-track invitation to submit an extended version of our ICAART 2021 paper "SAT-MARL: Specification Aware Training in Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning" (co-author).
- 2019 Travel Grant for AAMAS 2019, DAAD, Montreal, Canada
- 2016 Best Bachelor Award, Rohde & Schwarz GmbH & Co. KG, Munich, Germany
- 2016 Award for an Outstanding Bachelor Thesis in the Field of Image Processing, Stemmer Imaging GmbH, Munich, Germany
- 2012 2017 **Scholarship**, *Studienstiftung des Deutschen Volkes*, Munich, Germany In Germany, the top 0.5% of university or high school students get selected for funding by the German Academic Scholarship Foundation.

Research Projects

- 2023 Present Al4OPT Al Institute for Advances in Optimization, National Science Foundation, Los Angeles, CA, USA
 Research on multi-agent learning for optimization.
 - 2023 **Dependability of Machine Learning in Industrial Robotics**, *Siemens AG*, Munich, Germany
 Research on robust machine learning in industrial robotics. Assisted acquisition.
 - 2022 2024 Al-Fusion Evaluation of Emergence in Distributed Intelligent Systems,
 Bavarian Ministry of Economic Affairs, Regional Development, and Energy, Munich,
 Germany

 Personal on emergence in multi-agent learning in collaboration with Example for IKS.

Research on emergence in multi-agent learning in collaboration with Fraunhofer IKS. Assisted acquisition.

Thomy Phan 2/7

- Validation and Verification of Modular Machine Learning Systems, Siemens AG, Munich, Germany
 Research on modular machine learning. Assisted acquisition.
- 2020 2021 **Federated Learning in Industrial Environments**, *Siemens AG*, Munich, Germany Research on adaptive testing of federated learning systems. Assisted acquisition.
 - 2019 Dependability of Machine Learning in Industrial Environments, Siemens AG, Munich, Germany
 - Research on resilience in multi-agent reinforcement learning.
 - 2018 Coevolution in Machine Learning Based Industrial Environments, Siemens AG, Munich, Germany

Research on scenario coevolution in reinforcement learning.

2017 – 2023 InnoMI – Innovation Center Mobile Internet, Bavarian Ministry of Economic Affairs, Regional Development, and Energy, Munich, Germany Research on innovative mobile and distributed applications.

Selected Publications

Conferences

2023 [C14] Attention-Based Recurrence for Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning under Stochastic Partial Observability

Thomy Phan, Fabian Ritz, Philipp Altmann, Maximilian Zorn, Jonas Nüßlein, Michael Kölle, Thomas Gabor, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien.

International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), pages 27840–27853, 2023.

- [C13] CROP: Towards Distributional-Shift Robust Reinforcement Learning using Compact Reshaped Observation Processing Philipp Altmann, Leonard Feuchtinger, Fabian Ritz, Jonas Nüßlein, Claudia Linnhoff-Popien, and Thomy Phan. International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI), pages 3414–3422, 2023.
- 2022 [C12] Emergent Cooperation from Mutual Acknowledgment Exchange

 Thomy Phan, Felix Sommer, Philipp Altmann, Fabian Ritz, Lenz Belzner, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien.

 International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (AAMAS), pages 1047–1055, 2022.
 - [C11] Towards Anomaly Detection in Reinforcement Learning (Blue Sky Ideas)
 Robert Müller, Steffen Illium, Thomy Phan, Tom Haider, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien.
 International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (AAMAS), pages 1799–1803, 2022.
- 2021 [C10] VAST: Value Function Factorization with Variable Agent Sub-Teams

 Thomy Phan, Fabian Ritz, Lenz Belzner, Philipp Altmann, Thomas Gabor, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien.

 Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), pages 24018–24032, 2021.
 - [C9] Resilient Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning with Adversarial Value Decomposition

 Thomy Phan, Lenz Belzner, Thomas Gabor, Andreas Sedlmeier, Fabian Ritz, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien.

 AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), pages 11308–11316, 2021.
 - [C8] SAT-MARL: Specification Aware Training in Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning Fabian Ritz, Thomy Phan, Robert Müller, Thomas Gabor, Andreas Sedlmeier, Marc Zeller, Jan Wieghardt, Reiner Schmid, Horst Sauer, Cornel Klein, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien. International Conference on Agents and Artificial Intelligence (ICAART), pages 28—37, 2021.
- 2020 [C7] A Quantum Annealing Algorithm for Finding Pure Nash Equilibria in Graphical Games

Christoph Roch, Thomy Phan, Sebastian Feld, Robert Müller, Thomas Gabor, Carsten Hahn, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien.

International Conference on Computational Science (ICCS), pages 488–501, 2020.

Thomy Phan 3/7

- 2019 [C5] Adaptive Thompson Sampling Stacks for Memory Bounded Open-Loop Planning Thomy Phan, Thomas Gabor, Robert Müller, Christoph Roch, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien.

 International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI), pages 5607–5613, 2019.
 - [C4] **Subgoal-Based Temporal Abstraction in Monte-Carlo Tree Search**Thomas Gabor, Jan Peter, <u>Thomy Phan</u>, Christian Meyer, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien. *International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI)*, pages 5562–5568, 2019.
 - [C3] Scenario Co-Evolution for Reinforcement Learning on a Grid World Smart Factory Domain

Thomas Gabor, Andreas Sedlmeier, Marie Kiermeier, Thomy Phan, Marcel Henrich, Monika Pichlmair, Bernhard Kempter, Cornel Klein, Horst Sauer, Reiner Schmid, and Jan Wieghardt.

Genetic and Evolutionary Computation Conference (GECCO), pages 898–906, 2019.

[C2] Memory Bounded Open-Loop Planning in Large POMDPs using Thompson Sampling

Thomy Phan, Lenz Belzner, Marie Kiermeier, Markus Friedrich, Kyrill Schmid, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien.

AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), pages 7941-7948, 2019.

2018 [C1] Leveraging Statistical Multi-Agent Online Planning with Emergent Value Function Approximation

Thomy Phan, Lenz Belzner, Thomas Gabor, and Kyrill Schmid. *International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (AAMAS)*, pages 730–738, 2018.

Journals

AAMAS 2022.

1055-1063, 2020.

2023 [J5] Emergent Cooperation from Mutual Acknowledgment Exchange in Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning

Thomy Phan, Felix Sommer, Fabian Ritz, Philipp Altmann, Jonas Nüßlein, Michael Kölle, Lenz Belzner, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien.

Journal on Autonomous Agents and Multi-Agent Systems (JAAMAS), 2023. Invited from

- 2022 [J4] Specification Aware Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning
 Fabian Ritz, Thomy Phan, Robert Müller, Thomas Gabor, Andreas Sedlmeier, Marc Zeller,
 Jan Wieghardt, Reiner Schmid, Horst Sauer, Cornel Klein, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien.

 Springer Book of ICAART 2021, pages 3–21, 2022. Invited from ICAART 2021.
- 2021 [J3] **Productive Fitness in Diversity-Aware Evolutionary Algorithms**Thomas Gabor, Thomy Phan, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien.

 Natural Computing, 20(3): 363–376, 2021.
- $2020\ [\mathrm{J2}]$ The Scenario Coevolution Paradigm: Adaptive Quality Assurance for Adaptive Systems

Thomas Gabor, Andreas Sedlmeier, <u>Thomy Phan</u>, Fabian Ritz, Marie Kiermeier, Lenz Belzner, Bernhard Kempter, Cornel Klein, Horst Sauer, Reiner Schmid, Jan Wieghardt, Marc Zeller, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien.

International Journal on Software Tools for Technology Transfer (STTT), 22(4): 457–476, 2020.

2016 [J1] Ultra-High Resolution 3D Imaging of Whole Cells (Cover Story)
Fang Huang, George Sirinakis, Edward S Allgeyer, Lena K Schroeder, Whitney C Duim,
Emil B Kromann, Thomy Phan, Felix E Rivera-Molina, Jordan R Myers, Irnov Irnov, Mark
Lessard, Yongdeng Zhang, Mary Ann Handel, Christine Jacobs-Wagner, C Patrick Lusk,
James E Rothman, Derek Toomre, Martin J Booth, and Joerg Bewersdorf.

Cell, 166(4): 1028-1040, 2016.

Thomy Phan 4/7

Workshops

Workshop papers with a conference or journal version are not listed.

2023 [W4] DIRECT: Learning from Sparse and Shifting Rewards using Discriminative Reward Co-Training

Philipp Altmann, Thomy Phan, Fabian Ritz, Thomas Gabor, and Claudia Linnhof-Popien. *Adaptive and Learning Agents Workshop (ALA)* at AAMAS, 2023.

2020 [W3] The Holy Grail of Quantum Artificial Intelligence: Major Challenges in Accelerating the Machine Learning Pipeline

Thomas Gabor, Leo Sünkel, Fabian Ritz, <u>Thomy Phan</u>, Lenz Belzner, Christoph Roch, Sebastian Feld, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien.

International Workshop on Quantum Software Engineering (Q-SE) at ICSE, pages 456–461, 2020.

[W2] Insights on Training Neural Networks for QUBO Tasks

Thomas Gabor, Sebastian Feld, Hila Safi, Thomy Phan, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien. *International Workshop on Quantum Software Engineering (Q-SE)* at ICSE, pages 436–441, 2020.

[W1] A Distributed Policy Iteration Scheme for Cooperative Multi-Agent Policy Approximation

Thomy Phan, Lenz Belzner, Kyrill Schmid, Thomas Gabor, Fabian Ritz, Sebastian Feld, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien.

Adaptive and Learning Agents Workshop (ALA) at AAMAS, 2020.

Extended Abstracts

Extended abstracts with a conference or journal version are not listed.

2019 [E1] Distributed Policy Iteration for Scalable Approximation of Cooperative Multi-Agent Policies

Thomy Phan, Kyrill Schmid, Lenz Belzner, Thomas Gabor, Sebastian Feld, and Claudia Linnhoff-Popien.

International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (AAMAS), pages 2162–2164, 2019.

Academic Activities

Organizing Committee

2019 International Symposium on Applied Artificial Intelligence (ISAAI)

Program Committee

- 2021 2024 AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI)
 - 2023 International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI AI and Social Good)
 - 2023 International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI Main Track)
 - 2023 European Conference on Artificial Intelligence (ECAI)
 - International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (AAMAS Blue Sky Ideas)

Reviewer

- 2024 International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)
- 2022 2023 Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)
- 2022 2023 International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)
 - 2023 International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (AAMAS Main Track)
- 2018, 2022 International Symposium On Leveraging Applications of Formal Methods (ISoLA)
 - 2021 PLOS ONE Journal
 - 2020 International Journal on Software Tools for Technology Transfer (STTT)

Thomy Phan 5/7

Teaching

- Spring 2024 CSCI 599: Autonomous Decision-Making (Upcoming), University of Southern California, Los Angeles, CA, USA
 - Special topics lecture on planning, reinforcement learning, and multi-agent systems
 - Primary instructor
 - Syllabus available at https://classes.usc.edu/term-20241/course/csci-599/
- 2019 2023 **Autonomous Systems**, *LMU Munich*, Germany
 - Practical course for 12 18 master students on planning and reinforcement learning
 - Primary supervising assistant until summer semester 2022
 - Syllabus and registration count for summer semester 2022 provided at https://uni2work.ifi.lmu.de/course/S22/IfI/ASP
- 2019 2023 Working Group "Artificial Intelligence", LMU Munich, Germany
 - Voluntary working group for more than 100 bachelor and master students on current AI topics
 - Primary supervising assistant
 - Syllabus and registration count for summer semester 2022 provided at https://uni2work.ifi.lmu.de/course/S22/IfI/AIAG
- 2018 2019 Mobile and Distributed Systems, LMU Munich, Germany
 - Practical course for 12 18 master students on mobile app development and on-device machine learning
 - Secondary supervising assistant
- 2017 2023 **Student Mentoring**, *LMU Munich*, Germany
 - 26 master theses
 - 24 bachelor theses
 - 8 individual research projects

Talks

Invited Talks

07/2022 Emergent Cooperation from Mutual Acknowledgment Exchange, Workshop on Ad Hoc Teamwork at IJCAI 2022 (virtual)

Highlight presentation of our AAMAS 2022 paper "Emergent Cooperation from Mutual Acknowledgment Exchange" (main author).

- 06/2021 **Stability in Al-Systems**, Digitale Stadt München e.V., Germany (virtual) DigiTalk event on Safe Intelligence of the Digital City Association of Munich.
- 12/2020 Artificial Intelligence How Do Robots Learn?, Gymnasium Berchtesgaden, Germany (virtual)

P-seminar talk for high school students and the Junior Science Café.

03/2019 **Building Autonomous Systems with AI**, *University of Augsburg*, Germany AI workshop for students of the Software Engineering Elite Graduate Program.

Presentations at Conferences as Main Author

- 07/2023 Attention-Based Recurrence for Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning under Stochastic Partial Observability, Honolulu, Hawaii, USA International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML).
- 05/2022 Emergent Cooperation from Mutual Acknowledgment Exchange, virtual International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (AAMAS).
- 12/2021 VAST: Value Function Factorization with Variable Agent Sub-Teams, virtual Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS).

Thomy Phan 6/7

02/2021	Resilient Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning with Adversarial Value Decomposition, virtual AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI).
05/2020	Learning and Testing Resilience in Cooperative Multi-Agent Systems, virtual International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (AAMAS).

- 08/2019 Adaptive Thompson Sampling Stacks for Memory Bounded Open-Loop Planning, Macao, China
 International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI).
- 05/2019 Distributed Policy Iteration for Scalable Approximation of Cooperative Multi-Agent Policies, Montreal, Canada International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (AAMAS).
- 02/2019 Memory Bounded Open-Loop Planning in Large POMDPs using Thompson Sampling, Honolulu, Hawaii, USA
 AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI).
- 07/2018 Leveraging Statistical Multi-Agent Online Planning with Emergent Value Function Approximation, Stockholm, Sweden International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (AAMAS).

Other Talks

2019 Unitag: Artificial Intelligence – How Do Robots Learn?, LMU Munich, Germany
University event for gifted high school students from Upper Bavaria (Oberbayern).

Thomy Phan 7/7